<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letters sent from Venice. Anno. 1571 Containing the certaine and true newes of the most noble victorie of the Christians ouer the armie of the great Turke: and the names of the lordes &amp; gentlemen of the Christians slaine in the same battell. Translated out of the Frenche copie printed at Paris by Guille[...]d Niuerd, with the kings priuiledge.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1571</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14317</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24634</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101788</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837591</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837591</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1923</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14317)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1923)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1012:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Letters sent from Venice. Anno. 1571 Containing the certaine and true newes of the most noble victorie of the Christians ouer the armie of the great Turke: and the names of the lordes &amp; gentlemen of the Christians slaine in the same battell. Translated out of the Frenche copie printed at Paris by Guille[...]d Niuerd, with the kings priuiledge.</title>
                  <author>Preuost, Fleuri.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henrie Bynneman. And are to be sold in Paules churchyard by Anthonie Kitson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1571?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>In two parts.</note>
                  <note>Part 1 running title reads: The ouerthrow of of [sic] the Turkes.</note>
                  <note>Part 2 has separate title page, with same imprint, reading: The vvhole discourse of the victorie that it pleased God to giue to the Christians against the Turkes, and what losse hapned to the Christians in the said conduct. Englished by a Frenche copie printed at Paris, by Fleuri Preuost, priuiledged by the king.</note>
                  <note>Printer's device (McKerrow 138) on verso of C4, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Print faded and show-through, and some pages stained; title pages marked, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lepano, Battle of, 1571 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:1923:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1923:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LETTERS <hi>ſent from Venice.</hi> ANNO. 1571.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Containing the certaine</hi> and true newes of the moſt Noble vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorie of the Chriſtians ouer the armie of the great <hi>Turke:</hi> And the names of the Lordes &amp; Gentlemen of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ſlaine in the ſame battell.</p>
                  <p>Tranſlated oute of the <hi>Frenche</hi> Copie Printed at <hi>Paris <hi>by Guille<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> de Niuerd,</hi>
                     </hi> with the Kings Priuiledge.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Imprinted at London by <hi>Henrie Bynneman.</hi> And are to</hi> be ſold in Paules Churchyard <hi>by Anthonie Kitſon.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:1923:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1923:2"/>
                  <head>The ouerthrowe of the Turkes armie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Chriſten armie being in <hi>Theſſalonia,</hi> in the Hauen of <hi>Argoſtelly,</hi> and the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in the goulf of the <hi>Pante,</hi> they tooke aduiſe what was beſt to bée doone. The Lorde <hi>Don Iean</hi> of <hi>Auſtrie</hi> thoughte it not good to enter into the goulfe, but the generall <hi>Biuier,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Iuſtinian Barbaric</hi> thought that beſte, earneſtly exhorting and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuading to go into <hi>Bisterlo.</hi> For by this meanes (ſay they) they ſhoulde obteyne the victory: and they concluded that <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barico</hi> with eyght galeys ſhoulde goe to the entrie of the goulf, to aſſay if he could trayne out the enemie: And whiles this was reſolued, the Generall <hi>Biuier</hi> was aduertiſed, that fiftie of the Turkiſhe Galeys had lefte the armie, and were gone into <hi>Lenant.</hi> Whervpon the Lord <hi>Don Iean</hi> reſolued fully too enter the goulfe, and the ſixt of this moneth, being carried in <hi>Pregates,</hi> wente in perſone to
<pb facs="tcp:1923:3"/>take order and encourage all men to bée ready on the morow to the battayle.</p>
                  <p>On Sunday the ſeuenth of October, was all the Armie in a readyneſſe, the generall béeing in the middeſt with fifty galeys, on the right hande the Lord <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barico,</hi> vpon the lefte the <hi>Ioerin,</hi> and the <hi>Dorian</hi> in the arreregard behauing him ſelfe verye valiantly. The ſixe greateſt Galeys rowed thrée on front, with .ij. lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Galeys after them. Thus marched they in order, helped ſomwhat forwarde with a ſmall breathe, more fauourable to the enemie, and in good tyme diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the other army, whiche came cluſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring lyke a wood, withoute any order. For they thought (as after was known) that ſo ſoone as they ſhoulde haue bene diſcryed, our armie would haue fled, and that they woulde be ready to ſpoyle and take ſome of our Galeys. But ſeing that the Chriſten armie made forwarde ſo boldly, they began to put them ſelues in aray, in faſhion of an halfe Moone. Thus bothe the armies béeing approched with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Cannon ſhot, the ſyxe greate galeys
<pb facs="tcp:1923:3"/>did breake foorth, and pierced cleane tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the Turkiſhe armie, whiche they put in greate diſaray with their artille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: whiche acte may be accompted the onely and chiefe cauſe of the victorie. In the diſcharge of the great ſhot, the Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes were more galled than the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. The Catholyke Generall, and the <hi>Venetian</hi> general, hauing betwene them the chiefe <hi>Baſſa,</hi> boorded his Galey, and tooke it, and hauing cutte off the <hi>Baſſaes</hi> head, put it vpon a pyke, which <hi>Don Iean</hi> helde in his hande, as a trophée. <hi>Ochiali Baſſa</hi> with his galeys preſſed ſore the left ſyde: and all the bodye of the enemies charged the body of the chriſtian battail, when <hi>Dorian</hi> with the arriergard ayded the ſayd body: and on the other ſide <hi>Don Iean</hi> ſente to ſuccour the lefte wing, an other number of Galeys, where there were alreadye ſeauen or eyght <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetian</hi> galeys. In this maner foughte they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually from morning til night. But in the ende the Chryſtians obteyned the victorie. There were taken .Clxxx. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys of the enimies, xxv. were burned, xv. ſoonke, xviij. fled, whom the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
<pb facs="tcp:1923:4"/>purſued. The great <hi>Baſſa</hi> of <hi>Argier Gitride</hi> of the great Turke was founde dead. The <hi>Baſſa Ochiali</hi> fled with a fewe galeys. <hi>Fortua Baſſa</hi> was not found dead nor aliue. And the <hi>Baſſa</hi> whiche came in ſteade of <hi>Prely,</hi> is he whome before I haue ſhewed to haue ben taken &amp; kylde. There are ſlayne .xx. thouſande Turks, v. thouſand <hi>Scarataui</hi> and .xiiij. thouſand Chriſtians priſoners ſet at libertie. And they had taken into their armie to relieue them .xiiij. thouſande <hi>Spachi,</hi> whom they had leuied in <hi>Morea.</hi> The Chriſtians of <hi>Grece</hi> ſeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſmal number of Turks left, &amp; the whole ouerthrow giuen to the Turkiſhe armie, began to ryſe. And ſo ſoone as the Chriſtian armie turned to <hi>Corfu,</hi> they with the victorie of <hi>Seigneur Don Iean,</hi> béeing accompanyed with a <hi>Fregate,</hi> came to the generall, offring to follow what part ſoeuer ſhall pleaſe him to go, ſaying, to haue very wel knowne that the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetians</hi> are chiefe lords of the ſea, but that neuer ſo wel tried as at that preſent. It is maruellous, that in the ſix galeys which made the fyrſt point, were ſlayne but thrée perſons. And generally
<pb facs="tcp:1923:4"/>thankes be to God, the whole fléete hath had ſmall loſſe in reſpect of the great vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torye.</p>
                  <p>God fauoured the Lord <hi>Barbarico</hi> ſo much, that he liued til night, when being aduertiſed of the aſſured victorye, hie lifted vp hys handes too Heauen in token of ioy, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with yéel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vp hys ghoſte, being hurt in the eye with an Arrowe.</p>
                  <list>
                     <pb facs="tcp:1923:5"/>
                     <head>The names of the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>Lords and Gentlemen</hi> ſlaine in the battaile.</head>
                     <item>The moſte excellent Lorde, S. Auguſtine Barbarico.</item>
                     <item>The Magific Lord, S. Benet Laurence.</item>
                     <item>The Lord Andrevv Barbarico.</item>
                     <item>S. Iohn Coruaro.</item>
                     <item>The magnific Laudo.</item>
                     <item>The Lord Marin Contarin.</item>
                     <item>S. Cattauino Mallipirro.</item>
                     <item>The Lord Ierome Contarin, vvith three of his Couſins.</item>
                     <item>The Lord Frances Bion.</item>
                     <item>The Lord Anthonie Paſquin.</item>
                     <item>The Lord Theodore Balbi.</item>
                     <item>The Lord Iohn Baptiſt Benoiſt.</item>
                     <item>The Lord Iaques de Mezo.</item>
                     <item>The Lord Anthonie de Mallogani Candiot.</item>
                     <item>The Lord Alexander Littico de Affrani.</item>
                     <item>The Triſſan Veſantin.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:1923:5"/>
THe magnifique <hi>Lanfran Iuſtinian</hi> brought the firſt tidings of this glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous victorie this day at .vij. of the clocke in the morning, landing from oute of his galley at <hi>S. Markes.</hi> The Prince wente to méete him, and at the firſte gréeting the Lord <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> knéeling, ſaide: Moſte ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellente Prince, I bring vnto you the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the Nobleſt victorie that euer chriſtian men had. The Prince with his hands ſtretcht vp to heauen, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ked God, &amp; without any ſtay with all the Nobilitie which cluſtered togither, went towarde the Church queſtioning with the ſayd <hi>L. Iuſtiman</hi> by the way, and there cauſed ſonges and Himnes to be ſung, prayſing God, and with greate deuotion remained aboue two houres in the Churche. The people and all the Nobles aſſembled on euery ſide embraſing one an other, vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all ſignes poſſible of vnexpreſſeable ioy.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <opener>
                        <dateline>From Ancone.</dateline>
                     </opener>
                     <p>THere is newes broughte that there is a ſhippe of <hi>Raguſa</hi> that left <hi>Candie,</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:1923:6"/>thirtienth of September, which broughte newes that the Galliotte of <hi>Famagousta,</hi> in which was layde the munition, repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for certaine that the ſixte of that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſente Moneth, the towne was in good eſtate and helde out luſtily: Which if it bée ſo, the aduiſe of <hi>Meſſino</hi> of the fyfte day, which ſayd that the towne was loſt from the beginnyng of Auguſte, is not true.</p>
                     <closer>Therfore, <hi>Vnto God be all honour and glorie.</hi>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:1923:6"/>
                  <head>The French King to the <hi>Bishop of</hi> Paris, <hi>vvith expreſſe</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement for Publike thankes to be giuen to God for the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie ſucceſſe of the Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans againste the Turke.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lorde,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I am aduertiſed from my Embaſſador re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident in <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enice,</hi> of a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie victorie fallen vppon the Chriſtian armie by ſea againſte the <hi>Turkes,</hi> who being wholely vanquiſhed, left dead twentie thouſand bodies with one of their principall <hi>Baſsaes,</hi> fiue thouſande taken priſoners, a hundreth and .lxxx. Galleys taken, within the which were founde and ſet at libertie fourtéene thouſand captiues of chriſtians, and all this happening with a very little loſſe of the chriſtian armie, wherof I thought to giue you this ſpéedie report, to the ende you might procéede to giue God thankes, as well in oure chéefe churche of <hi>Paris,</hi> as in all other churches,
<pb facs="tcp:1923:7"/>within your Dioceſſe, with Proceſſions and other ſuch plauſible actions of thanks giuing, as are conuenient to congratulate ſo happie a ſucceſſe as it hathe pleaſed the almightie to beſtowe vpon chriſtendom. And ſo my Lorde I pray God to preſerue you in his holy grace.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>At <hi>Vantiour</hi> 
                        <date>the laſt of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>1571.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Signed.
<list>
                           <item>CHARLES.</item>
                           <item>And vnder neath. <hi>BRVLART.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>Vppon the indorcement is written. <hi>To my Lord of Paris, one of my priuie Councel, or to his Vicares or Deputies.</hi>
                  </trailer>
               </div>
               <trailer type="illustration">
                  <figure/>
               </trailer>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:1923:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>¶ THE whole Diſcourſe <hi>of the Victorie that it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed</hi> God to giue to the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians againſt the <hi>Turkes,</hi> and what loſſe hapned to the Chriſtians in the ſaid conflict.</p>
                  <p>Engliſhed by a <hi>Frenche</hi> Copie Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Paris, <hi>by Fleuri Preuoſt,</hi>
                     </hi> Priuiledged by the King.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Imprinted at London by <hi>Henrie Bynneman.</hi> And are to</hi> be ſold in Paules Churchyard <hi>by Anthonie Kitſon.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:1923:8"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1923:8"/>
                  <head>The whole and certein Diſcourſe of the victorie that it hath ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God to giue to the Chriſtians a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Turkes <date>.vij. Octob. ANNO. 1571.</date>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE</hi> diuine goodneſſe and clemencie of the mercyful Lorde and God, hathe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ben ſo pitifull and fauourable to ſuche as in their afflictions haue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged him, that the remembrance thereof, dothe altogither make vs as it were perplexed and aſtonyed: for in all our actions and dooings wée haue taſted and felte his clemencie and maruellous mercies, euen at the very houre when wée haue had leaſt hope thereof, as the wyſe man doth ſhew vs by theſe words: <hi>Men shall bee tickeled vvith an horrible fear, and euen vvhen they haue leaſt hope they shall maruel of their ſafetie.</hi> Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of wée haue good experience, when that (beſides the innumerable graces wée re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue dayly) he dothe make vs more and
<pb facs="tcp:1923:9"/>more to knowe his puiſſance by ſuch ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes as to vs ſéemeth altogether impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, whiche oughte ſo muche the more to make vs prompt and ready to magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his greatneſſe, to prayſe and exalt his holy name euerlaſtyngly. And therfore his maruellous woorkes ought not to bée ſuppreſſed or kepte in ſilence, but rather to bée publiſhed from nation to nation, that wée which depende vppon his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and mercie, maye render vnto him all honoure and prayſe for euer. The newes that is come to our knowledge, of the miraculous victorie that it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> his diuine Maieſtie, to giue vnto the Armies o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Emperour, of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke king, and of the Seigniorie of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetians,</hi> againſte the maruellous and inſupportable armie of the Turkes, for that cauſe is to be publiſhed to giue eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man aduertiſement therof by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe that followeth.</p>
                  <p>By a Letter written from the <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> bearing date the nynth day of Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tober laſte, it was aduertiſed that the Sunday the ſeuenth of the ſayd moneth the armie generall of the Emperour, the
<pb facs="tcp:1923:9"/>Catholike Kyng and of the Seignorie of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetians,</hi> were in <hi>Cheſauian,</hi> within the portes of <hi>Argoſtoly:</hi> and the armie of the Turkes was within the gulphes of <hi>Velapante,</hi> looking when the Chriſtians ſhoulde come oute that they myght giue them battaile, and fight with them. The Chriſtians béeing but a few in numbre in reſpect of ſo great and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable an armie as the Turks was (the which ſéemed rather lyke a Foreſt than a nauie on the ſea, being well nigh two hundred ſhippes and fiftie Foyſts,) made it ſéeme dangerous to enter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the goulfe to fight with them: for they were not equall in force to them.</p>
                  <p>The noble <hi>Don Iean de <hi>Austriche,</hi>
                     </hi> (brother to the Catholike Kyng, and Lieutenant generall of his armie) was aduertiſed, that Fiftie of his greate Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys were vnfurniſhed there where one parts of his force was: whyche gaue hym greate occaſion to haue the better wyll to fyghte with the reſte: To come to whiche purpoſe, hée ſent oute eyghte good Galeys to drawe oute the Turkes
<pb facs="tcp:1923:10"/>to fight: After the which <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yght <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the reſte of our armie dyd follow in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye good order well furniſed (with good hope by the helpe of GOD to come to good effecte.) They did diſcouer the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of the Turkes, who perceyuing the Chriſtians dyd approche, came in great diſorder to aſſayle them, truſting onely in their forces: But the Chriſtians put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themſelues in battayle in forme of a <hi>Creſſent,</hi> did compaſſe as well as they coulde, the Armie of the Turkes, and they did it in ſuche ſorte, (that by reaſon of the ſayde diſorder) after they hadde fought valyantly from eyght of the clock in the mornyng vntyll an houre after dynner, they béegan to obteyne victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, whyche continued vntyll nyght: and if it had not bene for the darkneſſe of the pouder and ſhotte, they had whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defeated the armie of the Turkes, of the whiche there eſcaped but onely xviij. Galeys. Whyche victorie was execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wyth ſo ſmal a number on our part, that it was little or nothyng in reſpecte of ſuche and ſo great a victorie.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1923:10"/>
                  <p>Aboute moue was taken the Galey of the <hi>Baſſa,</hi> (that was the Lieutenaunt generall of the Armie) whoſe head was carryed to <hi>Seigneur Don Iean de <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriche,</hi>
                     </hi> whiche after he had a good while helde the ſame in his handes, hée com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded it to bée put vppon the ende of a Pyke, and to be ſette vppon the for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte of the Galley for victorie, and for a trymphe.</p>
                  <p>Of all the Armie of the Turkes, there was none ſauid but the ſayd .xviij. Galeys, whiche were folowed a greate whyle by thrée galeys of the Popes, four of the knyghtes of <hi>Malia,</hi> and ſixe of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetians,</hi> and they came ſo néere them, that if the darkneſſe of the nyght had not fauoured them with the helpe of their good Ores, they had not gone to carie the heauie newes of the ouerthrow of the reſt of their armie.</p>
                  <p>There is taken by the Chriſtians Cxxx. greate Turkiſhe galeys and fyftie Foyſtes, oute of whiche Galleys and Foyſtes, haue bene deliuered xiiij. thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand chriſtians captiues with the Turkes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:1923:11"/>
In the ſayde Galeys and foyſts was founde great ſtore of munitions of war, the moſte parte whereof was deliuered to be ſente to <hi>Malta.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There was alſo .xv. Galeys of the Turkes drowned.</p>
                  <p>And there were .xxv. galeys burnt.</p>
                  <p>And there were .xx. thouſand Turks ſlayne wyth their <hi>Baſſa,</hi> whiche was the generall of their armie.</p>
                  <p>Beſydes fyue thouſande priſoners.</p>
                  <p>The loſſe that the Chriſtians had, was two Galleyes of the Popes whiche were drowned.</p>
                  <p>And one burned of the Knightes of <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fiue of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetians</hi> were loſte, of the which two were burnt and thrée drou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
                  <p>The generall of the armie of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eneti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> was ſlaine in the ſaide Galleys that were loſt, and .xx. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enetian</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen.</p>
                  <p>There is deade of the Chriſtians as wel out of the ſaid eight Galeys that were loſt, as of them that were ſlayne in the
<pb facs="tcp:1923:11"/>other Galleys, aboute two thouſande men, of the which there were foure Knightes of <hi>Malta,</hi> thrée <hi>Spaniardes,</hi> and one <hi>Italian.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Venetians</hi> amongs all the reſt did ſhewe themſelues very valyante, and they were the firſt that with great fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie did ioyne in combate agaynſt the ſayde Turkes.</p>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:1923:12"/>
                  <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ell beloued Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde heere that whiche may he faithfully vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d by the letter writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten from <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enice</hi> the .ix. of October laſt, of the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it hath pleaſed our good God to giue vs againſt the enimies of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Church. Therfore conſidering the times paſt and preſent, in the which God all mercifull, hathe deliuered and preſerued vs from a number of miſchéeues and daungers, with the which we ordinarily are beſet, without hauing any power of oure ſelfe, to eſcape the ſame, except the immeſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble pitie of oure Lord God ſhoulde helpe vs. We ought therefore to ſing continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally with the royall Prophet, the earthe is all repleniſhed with the mercie of our good God which dothe maintaine vs in his kingdom, in his faith, in his ſeruice and in his grace incomprehenſible: and
<pb facs="tcp:1923:12"/>let vs firmely beléeue that he hathe care of vs, and that he dothe kéepe and defend vs more warely than the Egle or the Henne doo their chickens. Let vs giue him therefore withoute ceaſſing, glorie, and preiſes euerlaſting, framing our ſelues to maruell at the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his mercie, that doth preſerue vs alwayes from eminent dangers and perilles.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="printers_device">
                  <pb facs="tcp:1923:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <head>ARMIPOTENTI ANGLIAE</head>
                        <figDesc>depiction of a draped female figure on a pedestal, holding the bridle of a rearing horse in each hand</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1923:13"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1923:14"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1923:14"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1923:15"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1923:15"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
